Guide to the Saltar family correspondence, 1759-1880 and undated RL.10063
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Letters to Mary Gordon, 1808 March 14 - 1819 August 21; 13 items
  - 1806-1810, receipts on one sheet for payments towards debt by J. Craige to John Morgan (Box 1)
    Receipts accounting for payments sent by Mary Gordon to John Morgan's account, money from John Craig or Craige for the sale of a farm, outlined in the bond document from 1818. Witnessed by George Morgan, Julia Bunyan. Contains name of Beatty along with Mary Gordon. See Beatty's letter to about papers connected with this sale.
  - 1818 January 2 (Bond) (Box 1)
    Mary Gordon to John Morgan for $2019.42
  - 1821 June 15 (Memorandum) (Box 1)
    "Memorandum for Mrs. Mary Wilbur respecting Miss Gordon's business at Pittsburgh" - concerns a land sale in 1814 that involved John Morgan.
- Letters to Frances "Fanny" Saltar, 1810 February - 1880 March 28, and undated; 153 items
  Consists of 153 letters to Frances Saltar, daughter of Saltar family matriarch Elizabeth Gordon Saltar. This series contains mostly routine updates about family and friends, including births, deaths, marriages, visits, health, and courtship, and offers a detailed view of high society and women's pastimes during the late nineteenth century. Frequent descriptions are given of society parties. Repeated mentions are made of photography (chiefly requests for photographs), literature, gardening, and painting. Letters from 1878 often include travel notes, notably from Rome and Paris. Four letters from the 1860s discuss the Civil War in Pennsylvania, inlcuding the whereabouts of various acquaintances in the Union Army, battles near Chambersburg, Harrisburg, and Carlysle, and African American troops. Furthermore, this series contains evidence of personal finance largely through notes to Frances Saltar from Joseph Drew, who appears to be her banker. Medicine and health issues are again prevalent, covering a variety of afflictions, including measles, cholera, and mental illness.
  - 1810 February: Henry McMurtrie to Frances Saltar (Harmony Hall to Magnolia Grove, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1821 February 1: Susanna Hartshorne to Frances Saltar (New York to Philadelphia, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1821 April 22: Elizabeth Smith to Frances Saltar (Philadelphia, PA to Mulberry Hill near Trenton, NJ) (Box 1)
    Mentions courting and coping with death
  - 1821 June 14: Sally Harth to Frances Saltar (Portland, ME to Mulberry Hill, NJ) (Box 1)
  - 1822 March 19: Elizabeth Williams to Frances Saltar (Shrewsbury, MA to Holmesburg, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1822 April 9: Mary Cline to Frances Saltar (Shrewsbury, MA to Holmesburg, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1822 April 16: Susanna Hartshorne to Frances Saltar (Brooklyn, NY to Holmesburg, PA) (Box 1)
    Mentions "The Spy" by James Fennimore Cooper
  - 1822 July 27: Emma Howell to Frances Saltar (Cherry Field to Tacony, Philadelphia, PA) (Box 1)
    12 grains of calomel for chills (medicine); Cherry Fields catches fire (mentions the African-American help often when describing)
  - 1822 August 3: Mary Gordon to Frances Saltar (Holmesburg, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1823 July 16: Mary Cline to Frances Saltar (Middletown to Reading, PA) (Box 1)
    Sore growth in a man's throat (health/medicine)
  - 1823 October 30: S.M. Thompson to Frances Saltar (Cherry Field to Philadelphia, PA) (Box 1)
    Opens with "I s'pose, as the negroes say"
  - [before 1826] June 5: Susan Howell (Montalbina, near Leonard Town, MD) to Frances Saltar (care of Emlen Howell, merchant, Philadelphia) (Box 2)
    Substantial content on meeting many officers during her visit in Maryland, courting, and condition of enslaved women and children in Maryland: "I believe I must give him up and take to a rich little planter who has been quite attentive, but I am fearful I have offended him, by speaking rather too warmly perhaps against slavery"; "it is astonishing how ladies who profess so much delicacy... can ever behold [the sights of indecently clothed slaves] without blushing." The letter begins with a description of the large mansion, Montalbina, where "Sue" is staying for a few weeks as a guest of the owner, William C. Somerville Jr., prominent plantation owner.
  - 1832 January 24: Elizabeth Saltar (cousin) to Frances Saltar (Trenton, NJ to Reading, PA) (Box 1)
    A quoted description of Niagara Falls
  - 1833 June 25: Lynford Lardner to Frances Saltar (Cincinnati, OH to Knox County, OH) (Box 1)
  - 1836 August 22: Anne Saltar to Frances Saltar (Holmesburg, PA) (Box 1)
    Description of her "beaux" (courting); description of a fishing party
  - 1840 October 11: Anne Saltar to Frances Saltar (Lisbon Farm, NJ to Magnolia Grove, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1842 January 16: Helena Pennington to Frances Saltar (Philadelphia, PA to Magnolia Grove, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1842 March 6: Anne Saltar to Frances Saltar (Lisbon Farm, NJ to Philadelphia, PA) (Box 1)
    Building a new church in Pemberton and the community effort it requires
  - 1843 July 24: Anne Saltar to Frances Saltar (Pemberton, NJ to Michigan) (Box 1)
    The ideal character of a nineteenth-century woman
  - 1849 May 11: Elizabeth R. Coleman (Pemberton, NJ) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1850 March 9: Elizabeth "Lizzie" Gordon to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    A genealogy of her grandmother's family
  - 1854 August 20: Elizabeth R. Coleman (Pemberton, NJ) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1855 July 11: Elizabeth R. Coleman (Pemberton, NJ) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1860 February 13: [?] (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1861 March 14: M.M. Saltar (Toledo, OH) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Women and Christian duty; Saltar family genealogy
  - 1862 May 11: Harry Lardner to Frances Saltar (Philadelphia, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1862 July 4: Maria Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1863 January 3: Sallie Pearson Coleman (Pemberton, NJ) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    A description of the Christmas festivities in Pemberton of the week prior
  - 1863 March 9: Henry Wharton (Philadelphia, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1863 May 14: Maria Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1863 June 8: Lucy Wharton (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1863 June 18: Frances Wharton (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Lengthy account of the family's experiences a few days earlier during an advance of Confederate troops attacking Chambersburg and threatening Harrisburg, Pa.
  - 1863 June 21: Maria Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Descriptions of the attack on Reading, Pennsylvania.
  - 1863 July 12: Lucy Wharton (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Mention of the Civil War, including a brief reference to an acquaintance who has joined Landis' Battery and the "fight at Carlysle" Pennsylvania [July 1]. Lucy lists several men and their military positions, chiefly officers. "Every man that we know either has gone, or is going to this 'civil war'."
  - 1863 July 30: Lucy Wharton (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Description of Maria's party, which Union General Franz Sigel attended.
  - 1863 August 8: Maria Tilghman (West Haverford, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Explains the circumstances in which her relative Benjamin Tilghman has taken command of the 3rd Regiment of African American troops, after having commanded the 26th of Pennsylvania. ("He [Benjamin Tilghman]... is convinced that [African American troops] are to play an important part in the suppression of the rebellion"). Also mentions the siege at Fort Wagner near Charleston, S.C. and the attack on Gettysburg.
  - 1863 August 5: Frances Wharton (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Frances returns to art; attempting to "fascinate" two men at a party; General Sigel courting Lizzie Gordon.
  - 1864 February 4: Sallie P. Coleman (Philadelphia, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1864 March 1: Frances Wharton (Philadelphia, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1864 April 5: Sallie Pearson Coleman (Pemberton, NJ) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1864 April 1: Elizabeth S. Morris (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1865 August 20: L. Saltar (Buffalo, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Mentions "Cholera Morbus"
  - 1865 October 6: Henry Wharton to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1867 November 10: Col. Henry to Frances Saltar (Fort Schuyler, NY to Pemberton NJ) (Box 1)
  - 1868 July 22: Dr. and Mrs. Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1868 August 25: E.S. Morris (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1869 March 28: Maria Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1869 May 31: [?] to Frances Saltar (Glendale to Reading, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1869 August 6: Fanny (niece) to Frances Saltar (Ft. Monmouth, NJ to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
  - 1869 August 28: Virginia Lardner to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Gardening (esp. planting flowers) as a woman's hobby.
  - 1869 November 2: Joseph M. Drew (Philadelphia, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Bonds and money transfer
  - 1869 November 5: E.S. and Wharton Morris (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Bump on lower left eyelid (medicine); finances of the sick
  - 1869 November 6: Mary Lardner to Frances Saltar (Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
  - 1869 November 8: A.B. Lardner to Frances Saltar (Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
  - 1869 November 16: Frances Lardner to Frances Saltar (Lynfield to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
  - 1869 December 30: Wharton Morris (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1870 January 1: E.S. Morris (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1870 March 28: Maria Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1870 April 21: Maria Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1870 June 28: Maria Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1870 July 28: Joseph M. Drew (Philadelphia, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Banking, bonds, and personal finance
  - 1870 August 31: E.S. Morris (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Speaks of incurable lung cancer and medicinal treatments.
  - 1870 October 23: Maria Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1871 February 26: Maria Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1871 April 15: Joseph M. Drew (Philadelphia, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    An annuity
  - 1871 April 19: Sophie A.M. Saltonstall (Toledo, OH) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1871 May 1: Joseph M. Drew (New York) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1871 May 16: Sophie A.M. Saltonstall (Toledo, OH) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1871 May 25: Mary E. Sizer to Frances Saltar (New York to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
    In an mention of party politics, a man is discharged from his position at the Custom House because he did not "favor their man in politics."
  - 1871 October 3: L. Saltar (Buffalo, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1871 November 18: Anna S. MacVicker (Chicago, IL) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Lengthy description of the aftermath of the Great Chicago Fire of 1871.
  - 1871 November 19: Mary E. Sizer (Buffalo, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Discusses a woman's responsibility to cook and entertain: "It seems to have become custom any nowadays for ladies to be subjected to the dictates of their servants."
  - 1871 December 3: [?] (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1871 December 10: Maria Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to New York) (Box 1)
  - 1872 February 21: H.H. Bowne to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1872 May 2: A.L. Henry (Briar Cliff Rectory, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1872 September 17: Laura (Kingston, [?]) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Eye problems (medicine)
  - 1872 October 10: L. Saltar (Buffalo, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1873 December 7: Laura (Kingston, [?]) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1874 March 6: Elizabeth R. Coleman to Frances Saltar (Pemberton, NJ to Reading, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1874 May 8: A.W. Smith to Frances Saltar (Philadelphia to Reading, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1874 May 17: [?] to Frances Saltar (Pemberton, NJ to Reading, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1874 August 4: Louise W. Hartshorne (Portland, ME) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1874 September 17: [?] O'Rourke (Shrewsbury, MA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1875 January 16: Louise W. Hartshorne to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Infant sickness (medicine)
  - 1876 September 9: Lucy (niece) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Mentions a man on "death's door" with typhoid fever.
  - 1877 February 1: A. Lardner to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Description of an inexplicable mental illness.
  - 1877 May 17: Maria Tilghman to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1877 May 24: Mary [?] to Frances Saltar (Buffalo, NY to Reading, PA) (Box 1)
  - 1877 June 13: A.L. Henry (Briar Cliff Rectory, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1877 September 18: A.L. Henry to Frances Saltar (Briar Cliff Rectory, NY to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
  - 1877 October 14: A.L. Henry to Frances Saltar (Briar Cliff Rectory, NY to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
    Discusses women's hobbies of copying books and taking or collecting photographs.
  - 1877 November 7: J.S.W. (Philadelphia, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1877 December 26: A.L. Henry to Frances Saltar (Briar Cliff Rectory, NY to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
  - 1877 December 31: Maria Tilghman to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1878 January 27: Mary R. Croes (Yonkers, NY)to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Reading "The Historic Mansions of Philadelphia" by Thompson Westcott.
  - 1878 April 2: Lucy [?] to Frances Saltar (Rome, Italy to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
    The author writes from Rome and mentions taking pictures, especially of the Vatican.
  - 1878 May 8: Charlotte McMurtrie (Bristol, CT) to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1878 May 10: A. Lardner to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1878 June 9: Maria Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
  - 1878 June 16: Helen Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
    Expectation to visit the Paris Expedition
  - 1878 June 27: Lucy [?] to Frances Saltar (Paris, France to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 1)
    Description of nineteenth-century Paris
  - 1878 July 8: A. Lardner to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1878 July 23: Helen Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1878 August 22: Maria Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1878 September 23: Helen Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1878 October 7: Maria Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1878 October 13: Maria Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1878 November 5: Helen Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1878 December 31: Mary Croes (Yonkers, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1879 January 7: Mary Daniel (Richmond, VA) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1879 January 18: Helen Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1879 February 2: Helen Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1879 March 2: Maria Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1879 March 4: Maria Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1879 March 8: Mary Croes (Yonkers, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1879 March 21: Ella H. to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1879 March 22: E.M. Hartshorne to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1879 April 17: Mary Croes (Yonkers, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1879 May 4: Maria Brooks to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1879 June 19: Anna Lardner to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA) (Box 2)
  - 1879 August 29: Anna Lardner to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1879 October 2: Lucy Drexel (New York, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1879 November 10: A.L. Henry (Briar Cliff Rectory, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1879 November 13: Maria Tilghman to Frances Saltar (Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1879 December 17: Anna Lardner to Frances Saltar (Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1879 December 25: A.L. Henry to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1880 January 12: Saidee Henry (Briar Cliff Rectory, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1880 January 25: Lucy Drexel to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1880 February 15: Helen Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1880 March 2: J.E. Stillwall, M.D. (New York, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1880 March 9: Anna Lardner to Frances Saltar (Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1880 March 16: Miss Bickle to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1880 March 22: Helen Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1880 March 22: Maria Brooks (Reading, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1880 March 28: Maria Tilghman to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - 1873 Feb. 19: Maria Tilghman to Frances Saltar [black border] (Box 2)
  - [1873?] March 16: Maria Tilghman to Frances Saltar [black border] (Box 2)
    Long letter with many details of the illness and death (of a child?) and Dr. Carson's diagnosis of possible meningitis, after consultation with other doctors. Other discussion of family members and coping with death, the death of Lawrence Lardner, and mention of Emily who was traveling in Italy and had to be told the bad news.
  - [1873?] March 17: Maria Tilghman to Frances Saltar [black border] (Box 2)
  - [1873?] Oct. 14: Maria Tilghman (Bryn Mawr, PA) to Frances Saltar [black border] (Box 2)
  - Oct. 5, no year: Mrs. Redmond (Burlington) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: Lillie [?] (New York, NY) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: Lucy Wharton to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: Fanny (niece) to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - Undated: E.S. Morris to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: Lucy [?] to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: Charlotte McMurtrie (Bristol, CT) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: A.L. Henry to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: [?] to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: Lucy (niece) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: [?] to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: L. Saltar (cousin) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: E.R. Coleman [?] to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: [?] (Philadelphia, PA) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
  - Undated: Tillie [?] (Locustwood, Middletown, NJ) to Frances Saltar (Box 2)
    The Hendrickson family had Locustwood built in the 1830s; their relations by marriage, the Hartshornes, wrote to Fanny Saltar beginning in the 1820s.
- Letters to Unknown Saltar Women, 1852 August 20 - 1878 July 16, and undated; 15 items
  Contains 15 letters addressed to unknown Saltar women. It is likely that letters from E.S. Morris and Maria Tilghman are addressed to Frances (Fanny) Saltar. Most content gives updates about family and friends.
  - 1852 August 20: M. Wharton (Philadelphia) to "dear Sister" (Box 2)
    On the death of Henry Lardner in Michigan, 1852, of possible bowel complaint brought on, it was rumored, by error in physician's treatment.
  - 1853 July 7: Maria Tilghman (Reading, PA) to "My dear Aunty" (Box 2)
  - 1857 January 20: Maria Tilghman to "dear Cousin" (Philadelphia, PA to Reading, PA) (Box 2)
  - 1857 February 8: Fanny Saltar (not Frances Saltar of Series 6) to "my dear Mother" (Box 2)
  - 1865 April 4: Maria Tilghman to "dear Cousin" (Philadelphia, PA to Reading, PA) (Box 2)
  - 1866 August 9: Maria Tilghman to "dear Cousin" (West Haverford, PA to Princeton, NJ) (Box 2)
    Attached: newsprint clipping of Pa. Railroad schedule
  - 1869 July 9: E.S. Morris to "dear Aunt" (Reading, PA to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - 1869 August 18: E.S. Morris (Reading, PA) to "dear Aunt" (Box 2)
  - 1872 March 16: H.H. Bowne to "dear Miss Saltar" (Box 2)
    Contains a partial family tree for the Bowne and Saltar families.
  - 1872 April 12: Amelia W. Smith to Maria [?] (Box 2)
  - 1875 September 10: E.S. Morris (Reading, PA) to "dear Aunt" (Box 2)
  - 1877 October 30: Helen Burke (Reading, PA) to "dear Aunt" (Box 2)
  - 1878 July 16: Dr. J.E. Stillwall (New York) to "Miss Saltar" (Box 2)
  - 1879 October 21: Maria Tilghman to "dear Cousin" (Reading, PA to Philadelphia, PA) (Box 2)
  - June, no year: invitation from Mrs. Wilmer to Mr. and Mrs. Saltar (Box 2)
- Other Materials, 1809-1872 and undated; 6 items
  Four items: a bond document; a sheet with receipts; a memorandum; and
  - 1809 (Envelope) (Box 2)
  - 1809 (Envelope) (Box 2)
  - 1829 (Envelope) (Box 2)
  - 1872 May 25: Envelope to Frances Saltar (Buffalo, NY to Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - September 19: Envelope to Frances Saltar (Pemberton, NJ) (Box 2)
  - December 9: Envelope to Frances Saltar (Reading, PA) (Box 2)